Guide to the Records of the Communication Arts Group RG.35.1
New York University Archives
Records of the Communication Arts Group
1946-1968
New York University Archives
New York University. Communication Arts Group
RG.35.1
2.5 Linear Feet
The collection primarily comprises selected files of Richard Goggin, professor of Film and Television at NYU from 1956 - 1980, donated to the University Archives over a period of just over a year, from December 1980 - January 1982. The collection is of value to researchers looking into the history of film, television and electronic media as an academic pursuit and the origins of the Tisch School of the Arts.
Arrangement
The collection is divided into two series with no subseries. The collection is arranged by category and chronologically.
Missing Title
Records of the Communication Arts Group
Committee for the Creation of a School of Creative Arts and Communication
Source of the Collection
The Records of the Communication Arts Group were transferred to the New York University Archives by Louise Ramsey, Assistant Dean, and were selected by Ramsey from the files of Richard Goggin, professor of Film and Television at NYU from 1956 to 1980. Professor Goggin donated additional CAG material to David Oppenheim, dean of TSOA, in July 1981; these files were subsequently transferred to the Archives in January 1982.
Administrative History of the Communication Arts Group
The Communication Arts Group (CAG), predecessor to the Tisch School of the Arts, was New York University's first attempt to integrate some of its many departments dealing with communications and the dramatic arts into one administrative unit. Organized in 1954 as a result of the Committee on Radio and Television's Proposal for a School of Communication Arts (1953), the CAG originally consisted of five departments from three schools: the Departments of Radio and Journalism of the School of Commerce; the Department of Motion Pictures and Television of Washington Square College; and the Departments of Dramatic Arts and Communications in Education at the School of Education. In 1957, the Department of Radio was transferred from the School of Commerce to Washington Square College where it merged with the renamed Department of Television, Motion Pictures and Radio. And in 1960, the Department of Journalism was also moved into Washington Square College.
The CAG was the coordinating agency for these departments of instruction between 1954 and 1966. While more than a department, the CAG was far from being a separate school and had neither faculty nor quarters it could truly call its own. Nevertheless, in its twelve-year existence, the CAG was involved in a number of activities, the foremost of which was closed-circuit television instruction at NYU.
The only administrators of the Communication Arts Group were the Executive Officer and his assistant. The Executive Officer made sure that classes, faculty, and facilities all meshed neatly together. He represented the various elements of the CAG to the University administration and to the deans of the respective schools that made up the Group. In addition, he helped make policy for the Group and participated in CAG projects, such as closed-circuit television and various communications conferences. Harvey Zorbaugh, professor of Educational Sociology and Anthropology in the School of Education, was the first and only Executive Officer of CAG, holding the post from 1954 to 1961. His assistant since 1956, Professor Richard Goggin, became acting Executive Officer in 1961 and held the position until 1966, when the CAG was succeeded by the School of the Arts (later named the Tisch School of the Arts). It does not appear that the position of Executive Officer was ever considered a full-time post; from 1956 to 1966, Goggin was also chairman of the Department of Television, Motion Pictures and Radio.
CAG members were dissatisfied from the beginning with the position of the communication arts at NYU. As early as 1954, the Executive Officer was pleading with the University administration for an independent school, devoted to communications and the creative arts. It was not until 1962, however, that the Ad-Hoc Committee for the Creation of a Communication Arts Center at the University was formed. Later, in February 1963, the University appointed a Committee for the Creation of a School of Creative Arts and Communications. In June 1964, the Committee made its final recommendations, all of which were accepted by the administration soon thereafter. It was not until the 1966-1967 academic year that the new School of the Arts was in full operation.
Scope and Content
The records of the Communication Arts Group contain correspondence, reports, minutes, brochures, proposals, printed material, charts, and photographs pertaining to the interests and activities of the CAG, 1946 - 1968, with the bulk of the material falling between 1955 and 1965. While the records touch on many areas of the CAG, they do not cover all of them in equal length or detail; for instance, there is limited material on the origins of the CAG. The records are primarily those generated by Professor Richard Goggin, assistant to the Executive Officer, 1956-1961. Upon arrival in the Archives, the records were in no discernable order.
The CAG files are divided into two series. The first series, "Records of the Communication Arts Group," are arranged into alphabetical subject files and contain a variety of material relating to the programs, problems, and administrative matters of the CAG, 1946-1968. Included are annual reports (1953/54, 1962/63, 1965/66), a few departmental reports, brochures, addresses of Professors Goggin and Zorbaugh, and records on curricula, facilities, CAG-sponsored conferences, WCAG and WNYU-FM radio stations, Sterling Forest Summer Theater, and the ANTA-Washington Square Theater. There is a significant amount of material on the Department of Television, Motion Pictures and Radio, 1946-1966, and on closed circuit television instruction at the University, 1955-1963. Although the CAG was not the only division at NYU involved in closed circuit television, it seems to have been one of the more important elements of the project. In addition, there are several files from the office of Radio and Television and the All-University Committee on Television. The relationship of these records to the CAG is not apparent but they contain pertinent CAG correspondence and were sent to Goggin in 1975 by the President's office.
The second series contains one document box of records of the Committee for the Creation of a School of Creative Arts and Communication (SCAC). Organized as an ad-hoc committee in 1962 and formally appointed with its final name in February 1963, the SCAC Committee was chaired by Goggin until it ceased operating in 1965-66; minutes, 1963-1964; and more than a dozen reports and proposals (from the 1953 Proposal for a School of Communication Arts to the 1964 Proposal for a School of Creative and Performing Arts) which trace the evolution in thinking about communications instruction at New York University.
The Communication Arts Group records, which neither all-inclusive nor comprehensive, contain important material on the teaching of communication arts at the University during a period when the subject was emerging as a legitimate discipline of academic interest. The records also illustrate the process by which the Tisch School of the Arts was founded in 1965. In addition, the records of the Communication Arts Group have a broader significance in what they relate about the growing importance of the communication arts in American higher education and New York University's leadership in this development.
Access Restrictions
Institutional records of New York University are closed for a period of 20 years from the date of their creation (the date on which each document was written). Board of Trustees records are similarly closed for 35 years from the date of creation. The opening date for files spanning several years will be 20 years from the most recent date. Access will be given to material already 20 years old contained within a collection that is not yet open when such material can be isolated from the rest of the collection.
Materials related to personnel, faculty grievances, job searches and all files included in the Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act (FERPA) are permanently restricted.
Related Materials
Records of the Office of the Dean of the School of the Arts: RG 35
New York University. Office of Radio and Television -- Archives; WCAG (Radio station: New York, N.Y.); WNYU (Radio station: New York, N.Y.); Goggin, Richard; Ramsey, Louise; Zorbaugh, Harvey; Stoddard, George Dinsmore, 1897-1981; Tisch School of the Arts
- Series I: Records of the Communication Arts Group 1946 - 1968, 1955-1965
  - Administrative Council, 1964-1966 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Annual Report 1953 - 1954 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Annual Report 1962 - 1963 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Annual Report 1963 - 1964 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Annual Report 1964 - 1965 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Annual Report 1965 - 1966 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - ANTA-Washington Square Theater, 1963-1964 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Art Education, Department of (School of Education): Training of Artists 1959, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Brochures, Drafts of CAG, 1957-1966 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Brochures, Non-NYU, ca. 1960 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Curricula (CAG), 1954-1956 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Dramatic Arts, Dept. of (School of Education): Sterling Forest Summer Theatre material, 1954-1965 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Facilities 1958 - 1960 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Facilities 1962 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Facilities ca. 1960s, 1960-1968 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Film Library (School of Education), 1963-1966 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Goggin, Richard (Acting Exec. Officer, CAG) Address, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Journalism, Department of (School of Commerce), 1954-1962 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Radio, Department of (School of Commerce), 1953 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Radio and Television, Office of (1954 - 1958) (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Radio and Television, Office of 1961 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Sponsored Programs: Center for Instructional TV, Summer Workshop, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Sponsored Programs: Mass Communications Conference: Correspondence 1963 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Sponsored Programs: Mass Communications Conference: Correspondence 1964 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Sponsored Programs: Mass Communications Conference: Meeting Notes, Jan. 1964 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Sponsored Programs: University Film Producers Association Conference, 1964-1965 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Stoddard, George D. (Vice Chancellor): Correspondence and Address, 1958-1962 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Televised Instruction, All-University Committee on, 1958-1961 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Television, All-University Committee on (later, All-University Committee on Television and University Development), 1948-1951 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Television, Closed Circuit: Correspondence 1955 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Television, Closed Circuit: Correspondence 1956 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Television, Closed Circuit: Evaluation material, 1956-1957 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Television, Closed Circuit: Inter-campus TV Link, 1962-1963 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Television, Closed Circuit: Memorandum: Future of Television at NYU, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Television, Closed Circuit: NYU-FRA Educational Workshop, 1958-1959 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Television, Closed Circuit: Questionnaires, 1958-1960 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Television, Closed Circuit: Report on Telecasts (Fall 1959) (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Television, Facilities, 1955-1960 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Television, Motion Pictures, and Radio, Department of (Washington Square College): Annual Report, 1961-1962 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Television, Motion Pictures, and Radio, Department of (Washington Square College): Columbia Pictures Scholarship Proposal, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Television, Motion Pictures, and Radio, Department of (Washington Square College): Curriculum: 1957 - 58, 1960 - 61, 1957-1961 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Television, Motion Pictures, and Radio, Department of (Washington Square College): Correspondence, 1946-1955 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Television, Motion Pictures, and Radio, Department of (Washington Square College): Facilities, 1958-1965 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Television, Motion Pictures, and Radio, Department of (Washington Square College): History, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Television, Motion Pictures, and Radio, Department of (Washington Square College): Arthur Mayer Scholarship Proposal, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Television, Motion Pictures, and Radio, Department of (Washington Square College): School of the Arts proposals, 1965-1966 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Title VII, 1958-1965 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Washington Square College: Commission on Coordinated Liberal Studies, 1963 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Washington Square College: Correspondence, 1954-1962 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Washington Square College: Graduation Requirements, 1957 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Washington Square College: Minutes of Faculty meetings, 1956-1963 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    Content
    Annotations by Goggin for Committee for Creation of School of Creative Arts and Communications
  - Washington Square College: Student Services, 1957-1962 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Washington Square Journal: Articles on Communication Arts Group, 1955-1960 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - WCAG/WNYU-FM (radio station), 1955-1966 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Zorbaugh, Harvey (Exec. Officer of CAG): Speeches, Sunrise Semester Questionnaire, 1957-1958 (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Series II: Committee for the Creation of a School of Creative Arts and Communication, 1959-1965
  - Creative Arts Center Program and Building Proposal, Harvey Zorbaugh, 1959 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - School of Communication Arts, Proposal, 1953 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, including proposal for Communication Arts Center, 1962 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence 1963 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence 1964 - 65, 1964-1965 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Minutes 1963 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Minutes 1964 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Drafts and Reports, 1963 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Interim Report; Recommendation for the Creation and Implementation of SCAC (Interim Report); Curriculum Proposals, 1964 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Proposal for a School of Creative and Performing Arts and New York University, 1964 (Box 6, Folder 10)